Guide to the Lotte Lehmann and Dorothy Waage Correspondence Collection M2099
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Lotte Lehmann and Dorothy Waage correspondence collection
1942-1976
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Baer, Carol
Lehmann, Lotte
M2099
1.5 Linear Feet (3 manuscript boxes)
Small collection of correspondence from soprano Lotte Lehmann.
Content Description
The collection includes correspondence from 1942 to 1976 from Lehmann to Dorothy Waage and a few other close associates, including Betty Alexander, Viola Westervelt Douglas, Frances Holden, Milton Novak, Fritz and Theresa Lehmann, John Ross Haas, and Rudolf Bing. There are also newspaper clippings, photographs, concert programs, documents, and a copy of a 1969 book of poetry self-published by Lotte Lehmann, "Gedichte."
Dorothy Waage was a dedicated fan of Lehmann; their friendship began in the early 1940s. She passed away in 2001 and her niece Carol Baer subsequently came into possession of the letters. There are no outgoing letters from Dorothy in the collection.
Biographical / Historical
Lotte Lehmann was born in Perleberg, Germany on February 27, 1888 and died in Santa Barbara, Calif. on August 26, 1976. As an operatic soprano, Lotte Lehmann, began her career in Hamburg and moved to Vienna in 1916. She performed French, Italian and German roles for 15 years, primarily in Vienna and at Covent Garden, becoming especially known for the role of the Marschallin in Richard Strauss' Der Rosenkavalier. In 1938 she left Austria and settled in the United States where she performed primarily as a singer of Lieder. She retired from the stage in 1951, but continued to be very active as a much revered teacher in Santa Barbara, California.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
This collection was donated to Stanford University Libraries by Carol Baer in 2014.
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research. Note that material must be requested at least 36 hours in advance of intended use.
Baer, Carol; Lehmann, Lotte; Waage, Dorothy -- Sopranos (Singers)
- Lehmann - Waage Correspondence, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Lehmann - Waage Correspondence, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  Existence and Location of Copies
  One 1943 letter is reproduced on the Lotte Lehmann League's website: http://lottelehmannleague.org/about-lotte-lehmann/private-life/
- Lehmann - Waage Correspondence, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Lehmann - Waage Correspondence, 1945 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Lehmann - Waage Correspondence, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Lehmann - Waage Correspondence, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Lehmann - Waage Correspondence, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Lehmann - Waage Correspondence, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Lehmann - Waage Correspondence, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Lehmann - Waage Correspondence, 1951 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Lehmann - Waage Correspondence, 1952 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Lehmann - Waage Correspondence, 1953 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Lehmann - Waage Correspondence, 1954 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Lehmann - Waage Correspondence, 1955 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Lehmann - Waage Correspondence, 1956 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Lehmann - Waage Correspondence, 1957 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Lehmann - Waage Correspondence, 1958 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Lehmann - Waage Correspondence, 1959 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Lehmann - Waage Correspondence, 1960 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Lehmann - Waage Correspondence, 1961 (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Lehmann - Waage Correspondence, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 12)
- Lehmann - Waage Correspondence, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 13)
- Lehmann - Waage Correspondence, 1964 (Box 2, Folder 14)
- Lehmann - Waage Correspondence, 1965 (Box 2, Folder 15)
- Lehmann - Waage Correspondence, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 16)
- Lehmann - Waage Correspondence, 1967 (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Lehmann - Waage Correspondence, 1968 (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Lehmann - Waage Correspondence, 1969 (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Lehmann - Waage Correspondence, 1970 (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Lehmann - Waage Correspondence, 1971 (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Lehmann - Waage Correspondence, 1972 (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Other Correspondents, 1933-1976 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  Scope and Contents
  Includes correspondence from Lehmann to others and to Dorothy Waage from others, as well as other letters between other correspondents.
- Programs and Documents (Box 3, Folder 8)
- Lotte Lehmann, Gedichte, 1969 (Box 3, Folder 9)